[ INSTRUMENTAL MUSIC ]
[ SHEEP BLEATING ]
[ MUSIC CONTINUES ]
Good morning .
Uh , would you get me Major Bernard
at his Whitehall number ?
Thank you .
[ TELEPHONE RINGS ]
Hello .
Thank you .
Alan ... it 's Gordon .
Look , you 're coming down here today , aren 't you ?
Could you pick up a book for me and bring it with you ?
It 's ..
[ INTENSE MUSIC ]
Gordon ?
Operator ? Operator ?
Oh , blast it .
Got cut off .
That was my brother-in-law .
Would you try and get through again ?
I 've got to go and change .
Yes , sir .
Operator , we 've been cut off from Midwich 2-5 .
Would you get it again , please ?
FEMALE # 1 : ' Hello ? Hello ? '
' Will you replace your receiver , please ? '
' Please replace your receiver . '
' Hello ? Hello ? '
[ ENGINE RUMBLING ]
[ TELEPHONE RINGING ]
[ WATER RUNNING ]
[ RECORD SKIPPING ]
[ BELL CHIMING ]
[ CHIMING CONTINUES ]
MALE # 1 : ' For more than an hour , you 're saying ? '
Yes , sir .
Perhaps something went wrong with his phone .
Ha , but this is what puzzles me , sir .
You see , I 've also tried the vicar
the general stores and the post office .
I can 't get any reply from any of them .
Well , country telephone exchanges being what they are ..
Yes , I know , sir , but , uh ... look here , sir .
Midwich is here .
Now , Fourth Brigade are running
that exercise of theirs all around there .
Well , I don 't suppose there is anything in it , sir
but I was wondering , as I was going down
for the weekend anyway , whether I
could , uh , have your permission
to leave earlier than I intended ?
Alright , Alan . Give me a ring later .
- I 'll be here till 5 : 00 . - Thank you , sir .
Oh , Alan .
- Yes , sir ? - Have a nice weekend .
Give my respects to Gordon .
I will . Goodbye , sir .
[ DOOR CLOSES ]
[ ENGINE RUMBLING ]
- Hello , Gobby . - Ohh . It 's Major Bernard , sir .
Well , Gobby , what 's happened to the telephones ?
I 've been trying to get through all morning .
It 's funny you should ask , major .
I 've just been sent to look for the bus
which hasn 't turned up .
We can 't get through by phone either .
[ ENGINE RUMBLING ]
[ TIRES SCREECH ]
Here 's your bus , Gobby .
GOBBY : It 's truth .
Better have a look .
[ ENGINE RUMBLING ]
Alright , Alan , you better get hold
of the local area commander .
- What 's his name ? - Ward Johnson , sir .
Oh , yeah . Tell him to call me if he wants authorization .
I 'll get things moving this end .
- Oh , Alan , - ' Yes , sir . '
Make sure the newspapers don 't get hold
of this for the time being .
If anything has got out of hand there
we don 't want any panic .
Report back as soon as you have any results .
Right , sir .
Get me south-eastern command , please .
Over here , sergeant .
' Set up the tug line system . '
' Bring your men over here , sergeant . '
' Over this way ! '
MALE # 2 : ' Look , the canary ! '
You needn 't go in if you don 't want to .
I 'll have a go , sir .
- Quite sure ? - Sir .
Hold it !
Be careful , now .
MALE # 3 : ' When you are ready , doc . '
Alan , what on earth 's happening - -
Just a minute . Oh , hello , doctor .
Glad you 're here . We may need you .
What 's wrong with him ?
That 's what we 're trying to find out .
Will you take a look at him , doc ?
Well , take off the respirator .
Pulse is normal .
Seems to be breathing normally .
Ah , I think he 's just fainted .
Uh , he 's coming around .
Alan , you better let me know what this is all about .
Doctor , when were you last in the village ?
Midwich ? Oh , after about 10 : 00 .
Had a couple of patients to see in Widmarsh .
Now there are roadblocks all over the place .
Alan , I 've got to get back . I 've got patients to see .
Well , my hunch is that all your patients in Midwich
are in the same state as this man .
[ GROANING ]
Alright . Alright , old chap . Take it easy .
Take it easy .
What can it be ?
To-to put a man out like a light
penetrate our respirators , do all this ?
Some sort of gas ?
No , it can 't be .
Any breeze would have blown it about a bit .
The edges of the area are as well-defined
as-as that hedge there .
[ EXHALES ]
Cold .
- ' What did you say ? ' - Ice-cold .
I 'm alright , sir . Only cold .
My hands are like ice .
[ AIRPLANE DRONING ]
Midwich to Charlie-Alpha . Midwich to Charlie-Alpha .
Can you see anything ? Over .
Everything looks alright from here . Over .
Let me speak to him .
Hello , Charlie-Alpha . This is Major Bernard speaking .
Can you see nothing unusual at all in Midwich ?
Nothing moving ?
No , sir , nothing .
Matter of fact , that 's odd . Nothing is moving down there .
' I can see some people , but they 're not moving either . '
They 're ... they 're lying on the ground .
As though they 've fallen ?
' Yes , sir . '
Right . Take it down slowly .
But pull up the minute you feel anything .
Feel anything , sir ?
' Anything unusual . '
Roger .
Still nothing moving , sir .
Taking her down .
Careful , now .
[ ENGINE RUMBLING ]
Easy .
[ RUMBLING CONTINUES ]
[ EXPLOSION ]
[ AIRCRAFT DRONING ]
There 's another aircraft approaching .
Send out a general warning immediately .
All aircraft to avoid this area
and not to drop below 5000 feet .
Yes , sir . Midwich to base . Midwich to base .
Emergency . I say again , emergency .
Warn all aircraft to avoid area five-mile radius .
Latitude 51 degrees , ten minutes , 30 seconds north .
' Longitude one degree , 11 minutes , 20 seconds west . '
Maintain minimum altitude of 5000 feet .
Out .
[ MOOING ]
Blimey ! Look !
[ DRAMATIC MUSIC ]
[ MOOING CONTINUES ]
[ WATER RUNNING ]
[ MUSIC CONTINUES ]
Ah .
Gordon ..
Darling , I 'm sorry . I.. I must have dozed off .
Well , look at the time . It 's almost 3 : 00 .
' Why didn 't you call me ? '
I 'd better go and see about lunch .
A-Anthea ..
I found myself asleep on the floor .
What an extraordinary thing to do .
Oh ..
I 'm ... I 'm cold .
Well , the fires have gone out .
Did you ..
Did we faint ?
' We must have blacked out . '
Why ?
Oh , I ... my hands are ... quite numb .
Oh .
Gordon ... what did happen ?
I don 't know .
[ ENGINE RUMBLING ]
- Alan . - You 're alright .
- You 're late . - I couldn 't get through .
" Couldn 't get through ? "
Alan , what did you mean , " You 're alright ? "
I mean , how did you know ?
Well , it 's an extraordinary thing but we seemed
to have blacked out for several hours .
- I-I know . - It must have been some ..
It wasn 't only you two .
The whole village fell asleep .
The whole village ?
All of Midwich was cut off
from the outside world for several hours .
[ ENGINE RUMBLING ]
Anything registering , son ?
No , sir . Nothing unusual .
Well , keep at it .
OGLE : Oh , Mr. Zellaby !
- Uh , yes , Miss Ogle ? - You see ..
Are these people from the telephone company ?
GORDON : ' Not the telephone company . '
- ' No . ' - That 's what I said .
I mean , if they want to pull a wool over our eyes
they ought try something better .
Yes . Well , I 'm trying to find - -
After all , we 're not stupid , are we ?
What 's happened isn 't natural .
Tell you what we 'll do
I 'll press for an official explanation
while you help to stop the rumors getting about .
Alright ?
Do you mind ?
- Soil samples ? Plant life ? - Yes , sir .
Even the bark on the trees , but I - -
Don 't forget insects
grasses , water , metals .
The sooner and more elaborate
these tests can be made , the better .
- Yes , sir ? - It 's quite alright .
This is professor Gordon Zellaby .
- Oh , yes , sir , certainly . - Alan .
Well , no one seems to have come to any harm .
A few cuts and bruises where they fell .
Lucky , no one was in their bath .
They might have been drowned .
Yeah . Hello , Mrs. Harrington .
Well ! I think the least they can do is
offer us some kind of compensation .
But you feel alright ?
No , thanks to them if I do .
And a large burn on my best dress into the bargain .
What the wife means is ..
Well ... you don 't hardly expect to drop asleep
before dinner , do you ?
Well , we 've established that whatever it was
was static , odorless , invisible .
It didn 't register on radar , it was non-metallic
it showed nothing on our Geiger counters .
You 've got the reports there , Gordon .
There are no signs of any physical
biological or psychological changes .
Well , that 's practically meaningless .
For instance , serious exposure to X-rays or gamma rays
need not have an immediate effect .
But these people have to be kept under observation .
- And yourself . - And my household .
It would be a bit tricky to put you all in the sanatorium .
In any case , my instructions are to keep
this whole incident out of the limelight .
National security , eh ?
If you like .
Well , until we know the cause
we shan 't know what to expect .
Since , you 're there , Gordon , suppose you keep an eye
on Midwich for us .
If you find anything , let us know through Alan .
No need for any direct contact between us .
More security , eh ? Ever cautious .
Gets under the skin , you know .
[ PIANO MUSIC ]
[ DRAMATIC MUSIC ]
FEMALE # 2 : ' Anything else today , Mrs. Zellaby ? '
No , that 's all , thank you .
I 'll have to get in a new supply of these pickles
if you go on like this .
Yes , I do seem to be getting through a lot these days .
Don 't I ?
That 'll be , uh , 17 and six .
Shall I add it to the account ?
Yes , thank you .
Oh , how 's the professor ?
Oh , he 's very well . Very well , indeed .
- Good morning . - Good morning .
[ DOOR SHUTS ]
- Miss Ogle , dear . - Yes ?
I think there 's going to be news
up at Kyle manor .
News ? What kind of news ?
Hello .
I said hello .
Oh .
How long have you been here ?
- Ages . - Liar .
I 've just discovered a fascinating thing .
Here are the plant samples we took that day .
Now this one , for example
a perfectly ordinary pelargonium zonale .
And you see what 's happening ? Exactly what you 'd expect .
If I made a 50 percent gra ..
Why did you kiss me like that ?
[ CHUCKLES ]
Oh , come on . What 's the secret ?
Something 's afoot .
Why are you so happy ?
Now , Gordon , I want you to sit down .
- Alright . - Keep quite calm .
There 's nothing to worry about .
Now ..
... we have apparently succeeded
in crossing a Zellaby Gordonias
with a Zellaby Antheam .
Just what the results will be
we shan 't know for some time yet .
I think you should sit down .
- Can I get you some tea ? - No .
A drink ! No , that wouldn 't be right .
Uh , feet up ? Something to eat ?
- Yes , please . - What ?
Uh , cheese , pickles , and half a dozen anchovies .
Recently my favorite diet .
Hadn 't you noticed ?
Mrs. Plumpton at the shop has .
I 've been too engrossed in my work
but we 'll change all that .
[ INSTRUMENTAL MUSIC ]
Thank you , darling .
You 've made my happiness complete .
And all the more so because I 'm old enough to appreciate it .
Now then , what was it you wanted ?
Cheese , pickles
and half a dozen ... anchovies .
Hmm .
I 'm afraid there 's no doubt about it .
Milly , I wish there was something I could say
to comfort you because I know the sort of thing
you 'll have to put up with from
some of the people in the village over this .
But you can count on me to do anything I can
to help you and your child .
But do you think that I 've , do you think that I could - -
Milly , I 've told you , there 's no doubt about it .
Now , if there 's anyone you want me to talk to about this ..
But I 've never ..
[ CRYING ] It 's impossible !
[
SNIFFLING ] ' It 's impossible . '
[ SOBBING ]
MALE # 4 : ' This is some present , Jim . Thanks a lot . '
' Where did you say you got it ? Tokyo ? '
Oh , it 's a real beauty .
You can take action pictures in this light .
Jan , look at me .
When I learn to use this properly
I might go into the photo business .
Jan , turn this way .
That 's right . I want to see how ..
What 's the matter with you ?
' Jim comes back after a whole year away '
' and you look as if you were going to a funeral . '
[ DRAMATIC MUSIC ]
An attempted suicide , Janet Pawle
whose husband only came back from sea yesterday .
Three other women in the village half out of their minds .
' Milly Hughes , Rose Shepherd and Mary Bernard . '
That 's why we 're asking you to tell us , Vicar .
Please don 't keep on .
Don 't you see that , what you 're asking me ..
... it 's not right , ethically .
Oh , for heaven 's sake , Vicar .
How do you think I feel ?
I married late in life .
When my wife told me that she was going to have a baby
it was my happiest moment I 've ever known .
Don 't talk to me about ethics .
Don 't you see that this is something
which concerns all of us ?
' That this is the one moment '
' when it is your , your duty '
' to break confidence . '
Very well .
Four of them have been to see me .
One of them is only 17 .
- Evelyn Harrington . - Yes .
She was terribly frightened , and frankly , so am I.
I know these girls . I 've watched them grow up .
And when they tell me that they have no way of accounting
for their condition well ..
... I 'm compelled to believe them .
That means that every woman in this village
who is capable of childbirth
is going to have a baby !
I can 't believe it .
This is not a matter of belief
Vicar , it 's a matter of fact .
And there 's something else .
All this seems to date from that day two months ago
' when Midwich was cut off from the rest of the world . '
[ INSTRUMENTAL MUSIC ]
Who 's next ?
[ MUSIC CONTINUES ]
This is Anthea Zellaby 's , doctor .
Let 's have a look at it .
It 's one of the most perfectly formed embryos , I 've ever seen .
Yes , but is it normal ?
It 's more than normal .
It 's a seven-month embryo after only ... five months .
[ DRAMATIC MUSIC ]
It 's alright , darling , I 've seen the X-rays
and it 's a fine specimen .
Dr. Willers says it 's perfect , absolutely normal .
That should make us very happy .
But it 's going to be alright !
Is it ? Is that what you believe ?
You 're tired , darling .
That 's right .
I 'm tired .
And do you know why ?
Because every night , I lie awake and worry !
Well , now you don 't have to worry anymore .
You don 't really believe that .
- Do you ? - Dr. Willers says - -
I don 't care what Dr. Willers says !
Alright , so it 's not a monster .
It 's a perfect specimen .
' But what does that tell me ? '
You 're going to have a baby .
Whose baby ? Yours ?
Does it tell me what-what kind of life is growing inside me ?
What sort of brain it has , where it comes from ?
Does it tell me that ? Where does it come - -
Stop it ! You must stop it .
Y-we-we-we 've got to be rational about this .
We may not be any better off than any of the others
but there 's absolutely nothing we can do but wait !
Gordon ?
Maybe it 's ours , maybe it isn 't .
If it 's ours , we shall know . If it isn 't ..
Gordon .
I 'm afraid .
I 'm so afraid !
[ ENGINE REVVING ]
[ INSTRUMENTAL MUSIC ]
[ GATE CREAKING ]
[ MUSIC CONTINUES ]
[ MUSIC STOPS ]
I hope that none of them lives .
What a ridiculous way to behave .
[ BABY CRYING ]
They 're terribly busy , Mr. Zellaby , but doctor said
to tell you that Mrs. Zellaby 's fine .
- And the baby ? - Perfect .
In every respect ?
Gordon , you got a cigarette ?
- How about the baby ? - Oh , splendid .
Unusually heavy , though , ten pounds , eight ounces .
Strange eyes . Oh , alright .
You can go in now . Got a cigarette ?
[ WHIMPERS ]
ALAN : ' Yes , of course . '
' How many others have been delivered so far tonight ? '
Anthea 's my third .
What about their weight ?
All slightly over ten pounds .
They 've all got these strange eyes .
All that worry , and now ..
Oh , Gordon . Have you seen him ?
He 's such a beautiful baby .
[ WHIMPERS ]
[ INSTRUMENTAL MUSIC ]
Gordon ..
... I do love you so .
[ GROWLING ]
He 's probably jealous .
[ GROWLING CONTINUES ]
' Now be quiet , Bruno . '
Lie down and behave yourself .
Handsome , isn 't he ?
Take a look at this , doctor . It 's a section of hair .
WILLERS : Yes . I-it 's flat on one side .
On the other , an arc .
Somewhat in the shape of a ..
... narrow capital D.
It belongs to my son David .
Have you ever seen such a hair type before ?
Have you noticed their nails ?
Yes . They 're narrower than ours .
Covering less of the upper surface of the digit
but as , as flat as normal nails .
What do the blood tests show ?
Oh , it 's too early to tell .
The blood circulating at present
is still that of the mother 's group .
So they 're apparently normal children
with these exceptions ..
Strange eyes , arresting , I would say .
An unknown hair group
and unusual fingernails .
Whatever they are , their physical development
is absolutely startling .
In point of time , they 're four months old
but their development and capabilities is ..
... that of 18 months .
ANTHEA : ' Aah ! '
[ DRAMATIC MUSIC ]
No , please , Mrs. Zellaby , you wouldn 't . No , no , please !
Aah !
She won 't stop , sir , she won 't stop !
Oh , Gordon .
[ PANTING ]
Now , what happened ?
[ PANTING ] I , I was giving David his ..
... his bottle .
I , I must have forgotten to test it .
It was , it was too hot for him .
' He , he spat it out . '
FEMALE # 3 : ' He just seem to glare at her . '
Get my bag from the car .
Is that any reason to scald yourself ?
[ INTENSE MUSIC ]
This box is a product of oriental ingenuity .
There are ... no visible means of opening it .
But if you do just what I 've shown you , it comes open .
Now see if you can do it .
Mm-hmm .
Down there .
- ' That 's right . ' - ' That 's right ? '
GORDON : ' Mm-hmm . '
' And that comes down , and .. '
[ MUMBLING ]
- ' Now you 've got it . ' - ' That 's it . '
Splendid .
Now you see , it shows that I was right
to marry your sister .
Your family has brains .
See if I can do this myself .
Alright , well , now watch this .
And remember that he 's only one year old .
Go on , open it , David .
[ DRAMATIC MUSIC ]
' Yes , there 's something inside . '
' It 's a chocolate . '
Come along . It 's time for your bath .
This is fantastic .
You think so ?
Come with me .
GORDON : ' It 's alright , Evelyn , it 's only '
' a box with a chocolate in it . '
I don 't know , sir , I never allow her to have chocolates .
Huh , well , it 's quite harmless , really .
I just gave some to David .
[ INTENSE MUSIC ]
But you didn 't even show her how to do it .
Well , that 's exactly my point . I didn 't have to .
If you demonstrate something to one of them
they all know it .
Now watch .
I want that !
Keith ! G-give it back to him !
At once !
[ INTENSE MUSIC ]
[ MUSIC CONTINUES ]
[ INSTRUMENTAL MUSIC ]
[ LAUGHING ]
[ DRAMATIC MUSIC ]
No , Nancy .
Leave them alone .
Ted Rowett ! You come inside this moment !
I 've told you about playing with those children before !
Where 's my Philip ? You 're always all together .
It 's his turn to study .
He 's at your home .
It 's his home , too .
You 're anxious for us to leave , aren 't you ?
You , you have the same every week .
Twelve jars , 15 shillings .
You wish we wouldn 't come here anymore , Mrs. Plumpton .
I , I never said - -
It 's what you 're thinking .
You 've nothing to fear from us .
However , in future , someone else will come for our order .
Goodbye , Mrs. Plumpton . Good afternoon , Miss Ogle .
[ BELL DINGING ]
[ DOOR SHUTS ]
Are you ready , Gordon ?
Some coffee ?
No , thanks .
Gordon , don 't you think Anthea should
know about this conference , what 's being discussed ?
There 's no reason to alarm her just because you 're alarmed .
I haven 't got your cold , scientific detachment .
People , especially children aren 't measured by their IQ .
What 's important about them is whether they 're good or bad
and these children are bad to everyone but you .
But they are children , Alan .
And children are not born with a sense of moral values .
They have to be taught .
With their intellect , that should be simple .
Intellect ? Intellect ? That 's all you care about .
What if you can 't teach them ?
' What if you can 't put the '
' brake of morals on them ? '
First we must try .
You 're blinded by this vision of intellect .
You see David as another Einstein !
Potentially greater .
Solving the riddle of the universe .
Your son , David !
Anthea 's son . I have no proof that he 's mine .
Where 's Father gone ?
Oh , to London .
You must hurry , David .
Why ?
You 'll be late .
No , I meant , why has he gone to London ?
He has some business there .
What sort of business ?
A conference .
Don 't you like me to help you , David ?
Thank you , but I 'm old enough to do things for myself .
Father agrees with that .
Darling , your finger !
Oh , let me do that .
It doesn 't hurt . Please don 't fuss .
It might turn septic .
There .
You said I must hurry .
Goodbye , Mother .
Goodbye , David .
LEIGHTON : ' And gentlemen , as the Home Secretary '
' has permitted this disclosure '
I can now inform you that Midwich
is not the only colony of such children .
Here , at a township in northern Australia
thirty infants were born in one day .
Apparently something went wrong .
All the children died within ten hours of birth .
In an Eskimo community , there were ten births .
The community didn 't take kindly to this .
Golden-haired babies born of black-haired mothers
violated the taboos .
None survived .
' In the communist world there were two time-outs '
similar to the one at Midwich .
One at Irkutsk , here ..
... on the borders of outer Mongolia .
A grim affair .
The men killed the children and their mothers .
Second , in the mountains of the northwest .
All the children survived .
Our reports , though limited
indicate that they 're receiving education
on the highest level .
All these time-outs happened on the same day
as the one at Midwich .
This is now three years ago .
Have we established anything about
the origins of these children ?
There 's very little to go on .
Zellaby , you must have some theory .
May I suggest that Zellaby may be somewhat
too intimately involved .
My position as a dubious father
is influencing my scientific detachment ?
- Is that what you think ? - I have reason to believe so .
Well , let 's hear what the others have to say .
Dr. Carlisle ?
I went into the question of mutation .
Once in a great many thousand years
an abrupt jump may take place
in animal or in vegetable life .
A new variation suddenly occurs for no apparent reason .
Would that explain why entire groups of people
were cut off for periods of several hours ?
No , sir . It would not .
Very well . Any other line of thought ?
Yes . There is the possibility of the transmission of energy .
May I put it this way ?
Already we can direct radar beams
out into space with the utmost accuracy .
Electrical impulses have been bounced off the moon
and we are continually receiving impulses
from other planets and stars
' and impulses are energy and matter . '
We 're aware of that , Professor Smith
but where does that take us ?
GORDON : ' The professor and I think alike . '
' What we can do , others , elsewhere in the universe '
' maybe able to do better . '
Exactly .
Let me get this straight .
You imply that these children
may be the result of impulses
directed towards us from somewhere in the universe ?
Well , of course , that 's just a theory
but there 's nothing to disprove it .
They may be a case of mutation .
They may be the world 's new people .
What we need is time to investigate ! Time - -
Just a moment , Zellaby .
Uh , General Leighton , you 've told me of some
developments at Midwich , what are they ?
A series of casualties , mostly among the village children
and each case after some contact with ... the others .
Children get into fights all over the world .
These were not fights in the normal sense .
No direct physical violence was involved
but two weeks ago , a boy , a good swimmer
was drowned in the Midwich pond for no logical reason .
Children also have accidents .
Gordon , you 've seen it for yourself .
The extraordinary power these children have
and the sinister way they use it .
Extraordinary power , certainly . Yes .
That 's precisely why we need time ! Time - -
In our view , it 's only a matter of time
before these children get entirely out of hand
with fatal consequences .
And what do you suggest ?
That they be shut away .
- You mean put in prison ? - Bluntly , yes .
You might as well do away with them altogether .
This isn 't a police state , yet .
But don 't you see what you 're doing ?
If you imprison them you 'll deprive
the scientific world of the greatest opportunity
it has ever had .
Opportunity for what ?
GORDON : ' For study . '
Gentlemen , a great deal has been said here
about the power of these children
but nothing about the nature of this power .
What we 're dealing with is a mass mind
an entirely new development
like a , like a colony of ants and bees .
These children all want to dress alike
and what one learns , they all learn .
I 've demonstrated this to Alan Bernard .
They are one mind to the 12th power .
' Now just think what it would mean '
' if we could guide it . '
' We could leap forward in science 100 years . '
At the risk of being destroyed .
What cannot be understood must be put away .
Is that your view , of the age old fear of the unknown ?
On the other hand , Zellaby , Leighton has a point .
There is a potential danger here .
We are gathered here as advisers
as scientists , as government experts .
Now , take a look at our world .
Have we made a good job of it ?
' Who 's to say that these children are not the answer ? '
- ' The answer to what ? ' - Well , to wars .
To disease , to human want and misery .
To all of our problems we 've been unable to cope with .
If they don 't make an end of us in the meantime .
We cannot throw away this potential
just because of a few incidents .
What is your suggestion ?
GORDON : ' I 'll compromise with Leighton . '
Let them live together under one roof in our village
where they can be kept under observation .
My department couldn 't accept the responsibility - -
I personally will assume full responsibility !
Just give me a year .
Mr. Home Secretary , I can 't agree to this .
But all I ask is a year .
Now , surely that 's not too much time
when so much is at stake .
' Just give me one year . '
Very well .
I will officially recommend your compromise .
Thank you , gentlemen .
[ INDISTINCT CHATTERING ]
Now , that 's as far as we shall go today .
Our next lecture will deal with structure .
' And by the way , don 't forget '
' you 'll be living here from tomorrow . '
Now ..
Why do you smile ? David ?
You don 't know how to put your question .
[ CHUCKLES ]
There isn 't much point in my trying to be subtle , is there ?
The question I was going to put was ..
By the way ..
... just how deep do you see into my mind ?
Everything that 's in the front of your mind .
The thought processes ?
The reasoning that leads to my spoken words ?
We still have to master that .
' It will come . '
Hmm . Well , that 's frank . Thank you , David .
At least I still have some privacy .
The question I want to ask is this ..
Are you aware of life on another planet ?
[ INSTRUMENTAL MUSIC ]
Then let me put it this way .
It is possible that life exists elsewhere , isn 't it ?
We don 't seem to be getting anywhere .
Why are you so nervous when an aircraft flies above you ?
You 're very observant , Father .
Yes , but that doesn 't answer my question .
Alright .
Until recently , we haven 't been able
to make our control reach as far as a high aircraft .
Oh , now you have , is that it ?
What are you going to do with that power ?
Father , we know what you 're trying to find out .
It would be better if you didn 't ask these questions .
We want to learn from you .
Alright , that will be all for today .
- David ? - Yes , Father ?
I 'll walk home with you .
' What I meant was that you don 't have to go , David '
' if you don 't want to . '
I 'd rather go .
' You mean that , because the others are moving '
' into the school , you feel that you must , too ? '
- ' Is that the logic ? ' - Yes .
Your mother is quite distressed about it .
I don 't really know why I should be .
Lots of parents send their children away to school
and David will only be half a mile away .
I suppose there 's nothing that 'll
make you change your mind .
No .
I think that 's all .
Thank you .
[ ENGINE REVVING ]
[ BRAKES SCREECHING ]
[ DRAMATIC MUSIC ]
I 'm very sorry ! It was all my fault .
You alright ?
[ DRAMATIC MUSIC ]
[ ENGINE TURNING OVER ]
[ MUSIC CONTINUES ]
MALE # 5 : ' Mrs. Zellaby , I wish you 'd be more specific '
in your testimony .
I know these things are difficult
but it 's our obligation to determine
the responsibility for this man 's death .
I find it very difficult to remember .
I..
You told constable Gobby
you heard the screech of his brakes .
Well , yes , that 's right .
He ..
He got ..
... out of the car .
Then what did he do , Mrs. Zellaby ?
Then he ..
... he got back into the car ..
... and drove straight for the wall .
Thank you , Mrs. Zellaby .
I don 't think we need go any further .
But it seems to be quite apparent what happened here .
' Edward Pawle , the deceased , his vision obscured '
' came close to striking and injuring a child '
' then , obviously in nervous shock '
' struck the wall . '
' I recommend that you bring in a verdict of accidental death . '
Mrs. Zellaby , you know they killed him !
[ INDISTINCT CHATTERING ]
Ask them ! Just ask them !
[ GAVEL POUNDING ]
Who is that man ?
James Pawle , sir .
Brother of the deceased .
Then I shall overlook this outburst .
Gordon , can 't you see now that
Midwich is living on top of a volcano ?
A force is building up .
Sooner or later it 's bound to explode .
We still haven 't any proof .
For heaven 's sake , how much more proof do you need ?
- The death of James Pawl - - - Alan .
I 'm much more aware of the situation than you think .
[ DRAMATIC MUSIC ]
- Jim ! - Why not ?
Look what they did to my brother !
This won 't bring him back .
Who 's going to stop them if I don 't try ?
You can 't stop ' em with that believe me .
' They 're not human ! They ought to be destroyed ! '
Go home , Jim . I said go home !
Leave here now , before they get any closer .
[ MUSIC CONTINUES ]
Alright , Mr. Zellaby .
[ INTENSE MUSIC ]
[ MUSIC CONTINUES ]
[ GUNSHOT ]
Alright , alright . I 'm responsible !
I never denied it !
' It 's quite possible that , but for me , these two men '
' would still be alive , I-I-I was a little optimistic - - '
There 's quite a shindig in London
they may be after your blood , Gordon .
Do you think that I care a rap about that ?
What beats me is that I failed to reach the children !
But the point is , they 're shouting for action .
Now , things have gone too far .
The village is very near panicky .
Oh , if only I could get inside
the children 's minds and read their thoughts
as quiet obviously they can read ours .
Doesn 't that assume they have thoughts in mind
as we understand them ?
Alan , it 's for you . General Leighton .
Excuse me .
Thank you .
Yes , sir ?
I see . Yes , sir .
It 's as though their minds were surrounded by ..
... a brick wall .
If only I could break through it .
ALAN : ' Yes , sir . Certainly . '
Have I your permission to , to pass this on , sir ?
Right . Thank you , sir . Goodbye .
I 'm afraid there have been grave developments .
The Russian army group in the western Urals
is equipped with a new type of gun .
It can project a shell up to 60 miles
an atomic shell .
And apparently , they tried it out yesterday ..
... on the village of Reminsk
where their children live
and the village of Reminsk no longer exists .
You mean everyone there ..
The entire place . They gave no warning .
They couldn 't evacuate the villagers without
the children learning what was to happen .
They developed more quickly than ours .
They 'd begun to , to take control .
' An attempt to move them with soldiers '
' proved disastrous to the troops and the adults . '
I see .
So , now I suppose we 're going to blow Midwich
off the face of the Earth .
No , no , but ..
... but in view of recent events
they feel your compromise has failed .
' Leighton feels you ought to move immediately '
' before it 's too late . '
Destroy them ?
Well , they 're , they 're meeting tonight
to come to a decision .
They want me in town .
[ DRAMATIC MUSIC ]
What I say is , it 's got to stop !
ALL : Yeah .
First Ed , then Jim Pawle .
The authorities don 't do nothing .
Are we going to wait until we all get wiped out ?
[ INDISTINCT SCREAMING ]
Alright then , those that are with me , follow me !
[ SHOUTING ]
[ INSTRUMENTAL MUSIC ]
[ INTENSE MUSIC ]
[ MUSIC CONTINUES ]
[ DRAMATIC MUSIC ]
David , come here .
I want to speak to you .
A man is dead .
We must protect ourselves .
The law exists for your protection .
It 's of no use to us .
Of no use to you , is it ?
If you think you 're going to be allowed to live by your own laws
laws we don 't subscribe to - -
You 're thinking of what happened to the others
in another country .
Yes , if you know about that , you should know what to expect .
- It 'll not happen to us . - You little - -
It 'll not happen to us because we have to survive
' no matter what the cost . '
[ DRAMATIC MUSIC ]
I don 't think you 'll go to London .
' We 're now the only ones left '
and you must learn that we 're determined to survive .
And that there 's nothing you can do to stop us .
You have to be taught to leave us alone .
[ INTENSE MUSIC ]
Leave us alone .
He 's out of danger now .
Go to the library . I 'll join you there .
I 've never seen a severer a case of shock as this .
It 's medically impossible .
For a while , he was totally paralyzed .
Now his pupils are returning to normal .
His pulse is less rapid . His color 's returning .
I 've never seen anything like this before .
It 's time London sent in some troops .
I talked to General Leighton . Troops are not the answer .
The children would only make them shoot one another .
Tonight should be enough for all of us , even me .
- What is the answer , then ? - I don 't know .
But no more people must be hurt .
WILLERS : ' Is there no limit to the power of these children ? '
No more than there 's a limit to the mind .
' David ! '
What do you want here ? I should have - -
I want to speak to my father .
David , why do you do these dreadful things ?
Wherever it is you come from
you 're , you 're part of us now .
Couldn 't you learn to live with us
and help us live with you ?
I want to speak to my father .
The effects seem to be wearing off ..
Major Bernard will be alright .
What we did was only to warn him ..
... and all of you .
- Leave us , Anthea . - But I - -
Please .
You are not afraid of us .
No ... but I 'm sorry , David .
I 'm sorry I was wrong about you .
If you didn 't suffer from emotions
from feelings , you could be as powerful as we are .
Yes .
You 'll never reach our minds .
I 've come to say it 's time for us to go .
Go where ?
Away from here before they try to destroy us .
What will you do ?
Spread out and disperse .
Soon we 'll have reached the stage
when we can form new colonies .
In the meantime , we 've attracted too much attention .
You must help us to leave .
How would you wish me to help you ?
You 'll arrange a method of getting us away from here
without attracting attention .
You 'll find a number of families spread over the country
that 'll take us in .
Yes , well , that 'll take a bit of organizing .
I 'll need a few days .
Yes , and be sure no one finds out .
Otherwise , more people will be hurt .
You 'll tell us the arrangements you 've made
when you come to give us our lesson on Friday .
David - -
You won 't be able to deceive us , you know that , don 't you ?
- Yes , I know that . - Very well .
Let us know your arrangements on Friday .
Good night , Father .
Good night , David .
[ INSTRUMENTAL MUSIC ]
A brick wall ..
Are you alright now ?
Yeah , sight 's still a bit foggy
but clearing all the time .
I 'll just go and tell Gordon .
[ PIANO MUSIC ]
Remember this ?
' You wore a dark blue dress . '
' Your hair was longer then . '
It caught the moonlight .
- We 're ready , Gordon . - Good .
- I wish you 'd - - - IT 'S 8 : 15 .
You 'll be in London by 9 : 30 .
I wish you 'd let me stay here or come with us .
Oh , now you know that isn 't possible .
I have things to do here .
And poor Alan would go into the nearest tree
if you let him drive .
Nothing like feeling useless .
You 're still going to see the children tonight ?
Yes . Every Wednesday and Friday .
After what happened ?
Especially after what happened .
I think I 've found a way of getting through to them .
And if I 'm right , we 'll have no further trouble .
How ?
I 'll tell you if I succeed .
Now , come on . I don 't want you to be on the road all night .
Here , now . This isn 't like you .
I know that ... it 's silly of me
[
SOBBING ] but I 'm afraid of them .
And I 'm afraid for you whenever you 're with them .
They won 't harm me .
In a strange way , they trust me .
Why , even David seems to accept me
divorced from my emotions , of course .
Alright ?
Off you go .
Alan , look after her for me .
I 'll give you a ring in the morning .
Yes . In the morning .
[ INSTRUMENTAL MUSIC ]
[ ENGINE CRANKING ]
[ MUSIC CONTINUES ]
A brick wall .
' Now , just think of a brick wall . '
I 'm sorry , old man .
You can 't come .
Look after your mistress .
[ MUSIC CONTINUES ]
[ ENGINE REVVING ]
- Alan ? - Mm-hmm .
- What did he mean ? - What ?
Why should he ask you to take care of me ?
I don 't know . Just a manner of speech , I suppose .
[ TIRES SCREECHING ]
What 's the matter ?
- Alan , I 'm going back . - Why ?
I 'm going back !
[ ENGINE REVVING ]
Good evening , children .
Tonight , we shall talk about atomic energy
and how discoveries made about 100 years ago
' completely changed our conception of the elements '
' and the place of the atom . '
You were to tell us tonight
what arrangements you 've made for us .
The place of the atom .
It 's 8 : 27 .
Why are you nervous ?
[ DRAMATIC MUSIC ]
Oh , the arrangements , yes .
Yes , I 'll tell you about those in ..
... in a few moments .
But first of all , I want to finish my lesson .
The question of
atomic energy .
You 're not thinking of atomic energy .
[ DRAMATIC MUSIC ]
' You 're thinking of .. '
... a brick wall !
[
THINKING ] A brick wall . A brick wall .
I must think of a brick wall .
A brick wall .
A brick wall ..
Brick wall ..
I must think of a brick wall .
It 's almost half-past 8 : 00 .
Brick wall ..
Only a few seconds more .
[ INTENSE MUSIC ]
A brick wall ..
[ EXPLOSION ]
[ INTENSE MUSIC ]
[ INSTRUMENTAL MUSIC ]
[ MUSIC CONTINUES ]